Inventory of the Virginia Taylor McCormick Papers 1887-1953
Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
Special Collections, Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
Virginia Taylor McCormick Papers, 1887-1953.
Special Collections, Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
Mss. 65 M13
206 items.
Papers, 1887-1953, of Virginia Taylor McCormick, Norfolk, Virginia, poet, literary critic, essayist, lecturer, and editor of The Lyric magazine, 1921-1929. Includes manuscript and printed poems; essays; lectures; and correspondence with other poets and writers.
Franklin P. Adams ,; Viscountess Nancy Witcher Langhorne Astor,; Baron Max Aitken Beaverbrook ,; Gamaliel Bradford,; Van Wyck Brooks,; Walter De la Mare,; Ellen Anderson Gholson Glasgow,; Rupert Hughes ,; Amy Lowell ,; Virginia Taylor McCormick,; H. L. Henry Louis) Mencken,; Marjorie Kinnan Rawlings.
Administrative Information
Restrictions on Access
Collection is open to all researchers.
Acquisition Information
Gift: 206 items, 03/21/1958.
Biographical/Historical Information
Virginia Taylor McCormick (1873-1957), of Norfolk, Virginia was a poet, literary critic, essayist, lecturer, and the editor of The Lyric, 1921-1929.
Scope and Content Information
Papers, 1887-1953, of Virginia Taylor McCormick, Norfolk, Va. poet, literary critic, essayist, lecturer, and editor of The Lyric magazine, 1921-1929. Includes manuscript and printed poems; essays; lectures; and correspondence with other poets and writers. Correspondents include Franklin Pierce Adams, Lady Astor, Lord Beaverbrook, Gamaliel Bradford, Van Wyck Brooks, Walter de la Mare, Ellen Glasgow, Rupert Hughes, Amy Lowell, H. L. Mencken and Marjorie Kinnan Rawlings.
Arrangement
Organization
This collection has been organized into 4 series. Series 1 contains manuscript and printed material, Series 2 contains correspondence, Series 3 contains travel diaries, and Series 4 contains clippings, writings, letters and memorabilia.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into series by material type.
Index Terms
Persons:
Adams, Franklin P. (Franklin Pierce), 1881-1960.; Astor, Nancy Witcher Langhorne Astor, Viscountess, 1879- 1964.; Beaverbrook, Max Aitken, Baron, 1879-1964.; Bradford, Gamaliel, 1863-1932.; Brooks, Van Wyck, 1886-1963.; De la Mare, Walter, 1873-1956.; Glasgow, Ellen Anderson Gholson, 1873-1945.; Hughes, Rupert, 1872-1956.; Lowell, Amy, 1874-1925.; Mencken, H. L. (Henry Louis), 1880-1956.; Rawlings, Marjorie Kinnan, 1896-1953.
Subjects:
Poets, American- -20th century.
Contents List
- Biographical material. (Folder 1)
  Checklist of Virginia Taylor McCormick's writings compiled from the scrapbooks, drafts, and other papers and published works presented to the library. Biographical material relating to Virginia T. McCormick.
  Series 1: Virginia Taylor McCormick Manuscript and Printed Material
- Virginia Taylor McCormick manuscript and printed material, 1922-1939. (Folder 2-8)
  Includes manuscripts, printed poems, essays, lectures, fiction, etc.
  - Virginia Taylor McCormick poetry manuscripts: clippings, typescripts, and manuscript poems., Approximately 75 Mss. (Folder 2)
    Includes a number of poems pasted in a copy of Dramaland by Lin William Price (New York, 1927).
  - Virginia Taylor McCormick's lecture notes about literary figures and literature., 19 Mss. (Folder 3)
  - Virginia Taylor McCormick's manuscripts and typed drafts of essays, fiction, and lectures., 47 Mss. (Folder 4-7)
  - Printed writings of Virginia Taylor McCormick from The Archive, The Personalist, The Catholic World, The Magnificat, The Westminster Magazine, The Sewanee Review, The Southern Magazine, 1922-1939., 21 items. (Folder 8)
  Series 2: Virginia Taylor McCormick's Correspondence
- Virginia Taylor McCormick's correspondence, 1922-1953. (Folder 9-10)
  (See also scrapbooks.)
  - Letters to Virginia Taylor McCormick, 1922-1953., 24 items. (Folder 9)
    The letters are from Lord Beaverbrook, William Bowlin, Gamaliel Bradford, Maude McClare Brown, Van Wyck Brooks, Ralph Tyler Flewelling, R. Grieve, Richard Guggenheimer, Leigh Hanes, Margery Gordon, William C. Huber, Edwin Markham, Frances Mason, Marjorie Kinnan Rawlings, Evelyn Norcross Sherrill, Beverley D. Tucker, Charles Leon Tumasel and others.
  - Letters to Virginia Taylor McCormick from publishers, 1922-1944., 5 items. (Folder 10)
  Series 3: Virginia Taylor McCormick's Travel Diaries
- Virginia Taylor McCormick's travel diaries, 1910-1930., 3 MsV. (Volume 1-3)
  - Travel diary, 1 August-30 September 1910. (Volume 1)
    Kept while on trip to Cherbourg, Paris, Strasbourg, Baden-Baden, Neuhausen, Zurich, Lucerne, Interlachen, Luzana, Bellagio, Milan, Genoa, Mozbeaito, Nice, Rome, Naples, Florence, Venice, Innsbruck, Munich, A [?], Salzberg, Vienna, Dresden, Berlin, Amsterdam, Hague, Antwerp, Brussels, Ostend and London.
  - Travel diary, 14 February-30 April 1929. (Volume 2)
    Kept while on a Mediterranean cruise which included stops in the Middle East (the Holy Land), Egypt, Basque Provinces, and Paris. She writes down overheard conversations.
  - Travel diary, 31 May-29 August 1930. (Volume 3)
    Probably kept by Dr. James Jett McCormick, while on a trip to England and Scotland. Playing golf. Exhibition of Bobby Jones. Tea with Ellen Glasgow. Paul Robeson. Humorous toast to William III. Lord Astor. Stratford-on-Avon. World War I.
  Series 4: Virginia Taylor McCormick's Scrapbooks of Clippings, Writings, Letters, and Memorabilia
- Virginia Taylor McCormick's scrapbooks of clippings, writings, letters, and memorabilia, 1887-1942, 9 items. (Volume 4-12)
  - Virginia Taylor McCormick's clippings, notices of lectures, and book review, ca. 1921 - 1923. (Volume 4)
  - Virginia Taylor McCormick's book reviews, columns in Ledger-Dispatch (called Book Talks), and articles about Virginia Taylor McCormick and The Lyric, 1921-1924. (Volume 5)
  - Virginia Taylor McCormick's poetry clippings, book reviews, articles, fiction and announcements of Virginia Taylor McCormick Voices of the Wind and reviews, 1924 - 1926. (Volume 6)
  - Virginia Taylor McCormick's fiction, essays, reviews of Virginia Taylor McCormick's work, poetry clippings, letter to Virginia Taylor McCormick from Will A. Percy, 1926 - 1929. (Volume 7)
  - Virginia Taylor McCormick's poetry clippings and poetry of others. (Volume 8)
    Issues of The Lyric, vol. 6, No. 4 and vol. 8, No. 2.
  - Virginia Taylor McCormick's poetry clippings; essays; news clippings, 1930-1938. (Volume 9)
    About Virginia Taylor McCormick; letters by Lady Astor, Mrs. Hayward Wallis, Elkanah E. Taylor, Gamaliel Bradford, R. Torrance, May DeV F. Cobb, Alan Steinbach, Frances R. Williams, Florence Stearns, Mary Brent, Frances Carpenter Huntington, David Morton, and Florence Dickinson Sterns; reviews of the Virginia Taylor McCormick's Radio to Daedalus and Charcoal and Chalk.
  - Reviews, clippings and letters concerning Virginia Taylor McCormick's Winter Apple, 1942. (Volume 10)
    letters from Mrs. Robert Baylor Tunstall, Ellen Glasgow, Leigh Hanes, Beverly Tucker, Archibald Rutledge, Mrs. John David Leitch, Julius S. Held, Julia S. Grandy, Colin MacRae, Mrs. Vincent Sheean.
  - Miscellaneous clippings collected by Virginia Taylor McCormick (poetry by others); family photographs, clippings by and concerning Virginia Taylor McCormick, (first page dated 1895). (Volume 11)
  - Letters, 1887 - 1928. (Volume 12)
    Letters are by Edwin Markham, Armistead C. Gordon, Walter de la Mare, H. L. Mencken, Amy Lowell, T. W. Tally, Olive Dargan, Beatrice Ravenel, J. B. Yeats, Caroline Giltinan, Thomas Moult, Galmaliel Bradford, Winifred Russell, Josephine Hammand, Anna Cogswell Wood, Lizette Reese, Margaret V. Smith, Marshall McCormick.